这节课是讲V形折
立体书中最重要的结构之一
开始先说下用的材料
比较重要的是
卡纸的选择
常见的是用160克卡纸
你也可以用更重的
[译:推荐230克左右]
现在用的160克的
另外胶水也比较重要
这里推荐透明万能胶
粘接强度大、干燥速度适中
水性胶水也能用
但是干的慢 不顺手
还可能把卡纸弄变形
导致成品不够沃野
用固体胶呢
干净 快捷 方便
做草稿是绝对没问题
但不太适合要长久保存
和拿来把玩的立体书
时间长了固体胶可能会开裂
立体书会散架
另外 就是得把剪刀
用的很多
这节课就用到这些
立体书需要基础页面
就是把卡纸对折
要多折几次 折到彻底
我觉得说三遍不过分
折完一边 翻过来
再缕缕另一面
这就是基础页面了
立体书有三项基本原则
第一项
所有立体结构要跨谷沟
第一个谷沟是中折线这个
第二项原则
谷沟两侧折线要平衡
谷沟的两侧要在基础页面立住
两侧得达到均衡
在这个例子里
谷沟两侧夹角是均衡的
基础页面上中折线两侧
也是均衡的
第三项原则
所有立体书都会有谷沟
这里的谷沟是在中间
两边粘着平行四边形
立体书打开时
也就是谷沟展开
产生的动能带动立体结构
和其他顺带元素
这有个例子
也是个V形折
基础页面打开谷沟
谷沟带起粉色色块
粉色卡纸两侧的
平行四边形也被带起来了
回顾下刚说的原则
立体结构要跨过谷沟
谷沟两侧要达到一种平衡
制造谷沟来产生动能
以上就是三项原则
来看下实际应用中的V形折
这有五种V形折
第一种是直角V形折
卡纸两侧均是90度
过
第二种是锐角V形折
谷沟两侧角
都是小于90度
过
第三种 尖角V形折
锐角形折的一种变体
顶点趴着
顶到基础页的很边上
不变的是
两侧折痕都是指向中折线
第四种
钝角V形折
立体结构里
两侧向中间的折痕
都是超过90度
最后一种
非对称V形折
长这样的
四个角都不太一样
绿色立体结构两侧角度不同
基础页上两边的角也不同
仍然有种规律
左侧立面角加基础面角
等于右侧立面加基础面角
这样又是平衡的
以上就是五种常见V形折
这节课着重讲
直角和锐角V形折
其他先退下
后面教程再详细说
我们从制作个直角V形折开始
拿一张卡纸
折彻底了
再拿一张做立体结构
来个骚粉色吧
剪一半出来
目测 大不走溜就行
对折 折彻底
翻过来 折彻底
折彻底！
折彻底说三遍不过分
我们想让立体结构
这样子立着
两边的角度都一样
操作如下
先合上卡纸 从底部翻折
翻个面 再折一次
需要剪掉角落
从中折线和折痕交汇点开始
剪的带点角度
剪掉多余部分后
这就是上胶水的粘点了
剪开后 粘口这折痕可以再优化下
一个一个来
搞定    一个
另     一个
立体结构就出来了
两侧角度是一致的
我们要把它粘到基础页上
V形折折起来时
是沿着V指向的方向落下的
现在这个就是朝向我这边
所以粘的时候
要靠基本页前面一点
离我远一点
向基本页粘时是比较灵活的
你可以粘成
这种比较紧的形状
也可以粘的很敞开
但是最大宽度
不能超过90度
否则
会站不住 趴倒
所以 离中折线谷沟
要小于90度哦
粘的时候 稍注意下
从一边开始
来 上一点胶
在粘口上涂匀
我习惯用小拇指粘胶水
这样 粘不到手的其他部位
我就可以让
其他指头同时做别的事
粘口一头靠着中折线
基础页谷沟确认粘上
放倒立体结构
上胶水涂匀
边缘都要涂抹到胶水
要确保折痕边缘都涂抹到胶水
折痕对于立体书非常重要
right up to the crease any measuring you
do always to the crease fold it shut and
here is the right angle V fold this type
of V fold the right angle V fold is
really good for architectural subjects
so here's one this is one I've made this
is a this is a right angle V fold
raising a garden it's raising
parallelograms so this is the first
parallelogram it's glued into this gully
of the V fold and then this is the
second parallelogram glued into this
gully
so as the page closes the whole
configuration lifts up and falls away
this book fantastic fairytales by Ron
van der Meer
is all made of this type of right angle
V fold so if we just skim through it is
the first one this is the V fold raising
this parallelogram house to the next
page this is the V fold in this case
it's more open
than the previous one and again you've
got a parallelogram here and you've got
parallelograms here glued into this
gully where the v-fold glues to the page
this is the third one again this is a
right angle V fold and this little table
here this is a right angle V fold
raising a parallelogram here as the page
closes you can see the main one this is
folding down in the direction that the
that the V is pointing and the table
that's folding down in the direction of
these pointing so they both fold away
from each other and this is the final
one
this is a big big right angle V fold
with an array of parallelograms this is
the first one glued into this gulley
this is the second one built into this
gulley this is the third one built into
this gulley as the page closes the whole
whole slew folds away when you look at
the pop-up it's not absolutely flat it
tends to be at a slight angle so when
you look into this right angle V fold
that way the fact that the page isn't
completely flat doesn't matter visually
but if you look at it the other way
around so you're looking into the
mountain fold of it if the page isn't
absolutely flat the whole thing sags
towards you so that might be what you
want is part of your design but
otherwise the way you cure that is you
move into the the acute angle V fold so
here's an acute angle V fold the
mountain fold is pointing towards you
the base doesn't have to be completely
flat and yet it still stands up stands
up upright it's also good in this type
if you're using it to the right angle V
fold because it's near the front of the
page you don't have much room for
illustration text or whatever you want
whereas this type the acute angle V fold
because the V fold down towards you you
can position the whole thing near the
back of the page and then you've got
plenty of space you know on your base
for more illustration more pop-up text
whatever you like
so you can just look at this book
this is beware of the storybook wolves
the paper engineering is by M Corrine
Fletcher lovely book here's a fairy made
of a fairy made of a v-fold the it's
actually an asymmetric v-fold the v-fold
is pointing up the page so as you open
the page the fairy falls out of the book
and as you close the page they're very
you know jumps back into the book so
that's a really delightful use of that
that type of design you know and the
fact that the v-fold folds down in the
way it's pointing so now I'll show you
how to make the acute angle v-fold so
you get get your base sheet and fold it
in half crease it really thoroughly
again and again right here's the piece
we're going to make the the piece we're
gonna make the pop-up with so fold this
in half crease it really well and then
whereas with the right angle V fold we
just folded straight across third from
the bottom edge in this case we're going
to fold it up at an angle so starting
about half an inch up above the bottom
corner this is the folded side fold it
up at an angle and the angle you fold is
that will determine the shape of the
pop-up that you that you make fold it
back on itself when you open this up the
creases should be giving you a downward
pointing arrow it's really important
that the arrow points down then if the
arrow points up less an obtuse angle
v-fold anyway we'll cut these cut the
bottom in to gluing tacks
right this is this is going to be your
pop-up this is going to stand like this
on the page look at how it is when it's
on the page whether the tabs are
actually going to overlap like if you're
going quite tight like this they're
overlapping so just trim a bit more off
so with these you can decide how how
close you want the the tabs to be
sticking to the spine they've both got
to stick the same distance from the
spine but or quite wide the wider you go
the more the the pop-up will lie down
and then the closer tighter you make the
angle the more the pop-up will stand up
so just again to make sure these the
angles on the page match we start by
gluing one side so this is glowing up
near the top of your page so you stick
down one side make sure the central
crease is lined up with the gully of the
base so here it is fold it into its
close position put glue on the other
other tab making a mess here
and then close the place
there is the acute angle v-fold so the
thing to understand with these to
control it if you want the v-fold to
stand up more either you make the angles
on the base smaller or you make the
angles on the pot that bigger if you
want it to lie down more either you make
the angles on the base bigger or you
make the angles on the popups smaller
and that's really that's really key so
now we just look at a few examples of
how these how these pop-ups are used
here's here's one this is the red bit
the red bit is an acute angle v-fold and
it's got a couple of tabs cut into the
top and that's holding this is raising
up this Bluebird so the whole thing
folds down forwards as you close it
here's another example this is a this is
an acute angle v-fold
raising a figure we've got a couple of
counter faults built into the into the
gullies where it where it joins the page
and those are what what raised up the
arms and we'll just have a look at a
couple of a couple of books so this one
is Sergeant charge and in this one if
you look at this this is the the V folds
are here you can see there's a V fold
underneath maybe looking at it sideways
on you can see there's a pair of v folds
and they're actually raising a whole
series of of parallelograms and the V
fold folds away in the direction it's
pointing so the V fold is pointing up
the page so as you open it it's pretty
good the way it makes all the figures
come down so this is some v-folds used
to raise parallelograms is another
example here this is planes of the Aces
designed by I think it's Keith Mosely
and this is a this is that this is the V
fold and
it's raising up this Center plane that
the plane is completely made of
parallelograms so this is the this is
the v-fold this is the galley the
parallelograms are built into that gully
is a whole array of parallelograms being
raised up up vertically as there as the
page opens and great bit of design that
one and then finally there's a couple
here there's some monster islands this
is I think from 1979 or 1980 it's one of
the really early sort of second wave of
pop-up books and so this one this is a
this is a spread based on the right
angle v-folds and you've got a couple of
counter folds at the top here so this
whole bit it could be like that and by
putting these extra extra creases in it
comes down and gives you this extra bit
of dimension that's a right angle refold
and then on the next page this is a
acute angle default giving you this
monster and the way these arms work
that's all to do with slots we do that
in adult another tutorial
finally and there's a little book called
pop fill pop fill and the first first
spread it's got a whole lot of these are
really tiny v-folds with just one side
projected up to give these these some
tree tops so as you are going to close
it yeah you can go on and the trees turn
into and they start being replaced by
machines they're still defaults all the
buildings are parallelograms that's
another tutorial so that's it for this
tutorial
everything I've talked about is in this
this book pop-up design and paper
mechanics and everything I've talked
about today is in this book
you